Guide to the McCall family papers,1749-1942.
McCall family papers,1749-1942.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
McCall family papers, 1749-1942.
222
4.6 cubic ft.
Correspondence, Diaries, Financial Records, Legal Documents, Maps/Charts, Newspapers, Photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Family papers include correspondence and diaries of Ansel James McCall (1816-1898).
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
McCall family papers, 1749-1942.
Family papers include correspondence and diaries of Ansel James McCall (1816-1898), lawyer from Bath, Steuben County, N.Y. Correspondence is for the most part with friends from Hamilton and Union College, including James F. Chamberlain, James S. McLaury, and Charles A. Loomis. Correspondence comments on Hamilton and Union Colleges, Democratic politics, plans for western colonization, the Anti-rent War, and other topics of contemporary interest. Early family documents include deeds and wills, and a diary and account book of Ancel McCall, father of Ansel James (d. 1815) concerning early years near Ovid and Bath, N.Y. Diaries of Ansel James McCall cover his years at college, various summer trips to the midwest and to Washington, a trip to California during the Gold Rush, and a trip to Europe in 1848. Other diaries include those of James McCall (son of Ansel J.) while a student at Cornell University in the 1880s; one of Sophia McCall (daughter of Ansel J.); one of James F. Chamberlain's visit to Lake Superior in 1855. There is also an undated history of the family by James McCall, uncle of Ansel J., written during the latter part of his life.
Also, a volume of newspaper clippings from the Civil War period, including many anti-Lincoln articles and the text of speeches and editorials by various public figures, including Horace Greeley and Gerrit Smith. Pages 73-88 consist of manuscript notes and quotations from speeches by Senator Rufus Choate and from an editorial by Horace Greeley. Leather bound with spine title: Cash book.
Includes two diaries by James S. McLaury at Union College, 1837-1838 and 1838-1839.
James Read papers, 1788-[ca. 1862], Box 7, 222b.
Correspondence and accounts relating to the Pulteney estate holding lands now mainly within Steuben, Yates, Ontario, and Wayne Counties, N.Y.; surveyor's sketches and indentures in Steuben County; daybook, 1802-1803; cash book, 1792-1795, and four letters of Charles Williamson; a list of deeds recorded of lands sold by Williamson, and thirty-three letters to him, 1792-1803; autograph letters of Robert Troup, Dugald Cameron, Joseph Fellows, and James Read; twelve page letter of accusation against Dugald Cameron, undated, unsigned; also, letters from Read's son, James, from Illinois Territory (1810) and California (1850).
Charles A. Loomis papers, 1806-1898, Box 8, 222c.
Diary (1806-1815) and a journal (1825) written by Chester Loomis includes comments on the War of 1812 and other current affairs and describes life in the midwest; copybooks of Benjamin Loomis, brother of Chester; and letters of Charles Loomis, including letters from Ansel J. McCall whom he appointed to handle his business affairs in the Steuben County area.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cameron, Dugald.; Chamberlain, James F.; Fellows, Joseph.; Loomis, Charles A.; Loomis, Benjamin.; Loomis, Chester.; McCall family.; McCall, Ancel.; McCall, Ansel J.; McCall, Ansel James, 1816-1898.; McCall, James.; McCall, Sophia.; McLaury, James S.; Read, James.; Read, James H.; Troup, Robert, 1757-1832.; Williamson, Charles.; Cornell University--Students.; Hamilton College.; Union College.
Subjects:
Antirent War, N.Y., 1839-1846.; Family--New York (State)--Bath.; Gold mines and mining--California.; Lawyers.; Real property--New York (State)--Steuben County.; Real property--New York (State)--Yates County.; Real property--New York (State)--Ontario County.; Real property--New York (State)--Wayne County.; Surveyors.; West (U.S.)--History--1848-1950.; Women's diaries.
Places:
Bath (N.Y.)--History.; Europe--Description and travel.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1850.; New York (State--Politics and government--1865-1950.; Ovid (N.Y.)--History.; Pulteney Estate (N.Y.); Steuben County (N.Y.)--History, Local.; United States--History--War of 1812.
Form and Genre Terms:
Account books.; Daybooks.; Diaries.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Ansel James McCall Papers
Series II. Diaries and Books
Series III. James Read Papers
Series IV. Charles A. Loomis Papers
Series V. James B. Ellas Family Papers
Series VI. John Magee Papers
Series VII. Clippings and Pictures
CONTAINER LIST
- Ansel James McCall Papers, 1749-1942
  - 1749-1819 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1820-1835 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1836-1837 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1838 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1839 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1840 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1841-1842 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1843-September 1844, 1843-1844-09 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - October 1844-December 1844, 1844-10-1844-12 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - January 1845-July 1845, 1845-01-1845-07 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - August 1845-December 1845, 1845-08-1845-12 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1846 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1847 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1848 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1849-1850 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - January 1851-June 1851, 1851-01-1851-06 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - July 1851-December 1851, 1851-07-1851-12 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - January 1852-June 1852, 1852-01-1852-06 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - July 1852-December 1852, 1852-07-1852-12 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - January 1853-June 1853, 1853-01-1853-06 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - July 1853-December 1853, 1853-07-1853-12 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1854 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1855 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - January 1856-July 1856, 1856-01-1856-07 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - August 1856-December 1856, 1856-08-1856-12 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - January 1857-July 1857, 1857-01-1857-07 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - August 1857-December 1857, 1857-08-1857-12 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1858 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1859 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1860 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1861 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1862-1863 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1865-1870 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1871-1874 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 1875-1876 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 1877-1881 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - January 1882-December 1883, 1882-01-1883-12 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1884 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - January 1885-July 1886, 1885-01-1886-07 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - January 1886-December 1887, 1886-08-1887-12 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1888 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1889 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1890 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1891 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1892 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1893-1894 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 1895-1896 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 1897-1918 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 1825-1942 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Whitney Family Clippings from Mount Pleasant, Iowa, 1883, 1887, 1892 (Box 4)
  - John Mackay Clippings, 1890 (Box 4)
  - Undated correspondence, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Undated items, Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Undated items, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, Friendship Weekly Register, Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, anti-Masonry and William Morgan, Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Undated items, Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Assorted printed matter, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Assorted clippings, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Envelopes, photographs, Undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Undated clippings, Undated (Box 5)
  - Currency, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Diaries and Books, 1797-1890
  - Arithmetic Copy Books, 1802; McCall, Ann Shannon (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Diary and Account Book by Ansel McCall, 1797-1807, 1807-1811 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Diary of Ansel James McCall, 1835-1836 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Account book and itinerary of Ansel James McCall, 1830, 1836 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Diary of Ansel James McCall with annual annotations 1840-1890, 1837-1839, 1840-1890 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Diary of Ansel James McCall, 1837-11-1838 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Susquehanna River
  - Diary of Ansel James McCall, 1839-1840 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Washington, D.C.
  - Diaries of European and California trips with account books, 1846-1853 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Diaries and account books, 1855-1861 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Lake Superior, Chamberlain
  - Diary of Sophia McCall and Ansel J. McCall's account books, 1867-1877 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Diaries, assignment books, and account books from James McCall, 1882-1884 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - William C. Tieze's account books, 1870-1884 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - "A Narrative by of the Anti-Masonick Excitement in the Western Post of the State of New York", 1828-1829; Brown, Henry (Box 6, Folder 14)
- James Read Papers, 1788-1862
  - 1788-1795 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1796-1801 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1802-1805 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 1806-1815 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 1816-1821 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1822-1839 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 1840-1856 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Undated Pulteney Estate, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Undated Pulteney Estate, Undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Charles Williamson's cash book and day book, 1792-1795, 1802-1803 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Papers, S. H. Hammond, 1862 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "Absracts from Contracts of Sale shewing (sic.) the lots sold in the several Townships in the Third Range", 1803-1817 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Charles A. Loomis Papers, 1821-1898
  - Charles A. Loomis correspondence, 1821-1839 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Charles A. Loomis correspondence, 1840-1845 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Charles A. Loomis correspondence, 1846-1850 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Charles A. Loomis correspondence, 1851-1869 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Charles A. Loomis correspondence, 1870-1881 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Charles A. Loomis correspondence, 1882-1898 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Charles A. Loomis correspondence, Undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Charles A. Loomis correspondence, Undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Charles A. Loomis correspondence, Undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Charles A. Loomis correspondence envelopes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Copy books and manuscripts, Undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - 2 volumes collected by Benjamin Loomis and Vol. 2 of an analysis of Blackstone's Commentaries by William Leigh Pierce, 1809-1810, Undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Charles A. Loomis correspondence, 1806-1815 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- James B. Ellas Family Papers, 1808-1897
  - 1808-1838 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1839-1846 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 1847-1859 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 1860-1863 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 1864 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1865-1870 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1871-1897 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Jemima Wilkinson, Undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Notes, Receipts, and Envelopes, Undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
- John Magee Papers, 1823-1851, 1860-1868, 192
  - 1823-1828 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 1830-1851 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 1868 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - A sketch of the Life of General William Kernan by Alice Kernan, Undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "Huguenots of Westchester", 1864; Waldron, W. W. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "The Iroquois Trail", 1892; Beauchamp, W. M. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook by William H. Shepard, 1860 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Clippings and Pictures, Undated
  - Newspaper Clippings, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Picture Collections, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Maps and printed pamphlets, Undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Picture Collection, Undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Undated (Box 11, Folder 7)